בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is ס"ג, Samech Gimmel, 63.
We pick up with the top of ס"ג, Samech Gimmel, or actually
we can read the last line of ס"ב עמוד ב'. Samech Beis
Amud Beis. The issue here at stake is we're getting into all
these discussions about the definitions of ריבית. Ribbis.
The גמרא Gemara initially, not necessarily based on the משנה, Mishna, but
whatever, the גמרא Gemara initially basically said that although the תורה Torah
seems to distinguish between the phrases נשך Neshech and ריבית Ribbis as
מרבית, Marbis, one is about food and the other is about money.
את כספך לא תתן לו בנשך ובמרבית לא תתן אכלך. Es kaspecha
lo sitain lo beneshech ube-marbis lo sitain ochlecha. The גמרא Gemara basically
said that they both equally refer to food and money and really
anything that you could would lend and you would charge interest. נשך
Neshech refers to the impact on the borrower, to be נושך, noshaich,
to bite into him, and מרבית Marbis refers to the impact on
the lender, to be מרבית, marbis, to increase gain unjustly here, even
though it's really a deal, but whatever. I mean it's not stealing
or anything. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara says that those apply equally to
both. It actually also goes through an interesting discussion about why you
need separate prohibitions for גזילה, gezeila, אונאה, ona'ah, and ריבית. Ribbis. We're
left wondering to what degree would something like ריבית Ribbis actually be
considered a form of גזילה, gezeila,
because the person is doing it knowingly. And actually the גמרא Gemara
states that if the heirs, the children, don't have an obligation to
return the interest, and there's even a question whether the lender, the
children of the lender, and there's even a question whether the lender
himself has an obligation to return the interest, because he's really taking
money that the person agreed to pay. So he might be עובר
over on a prohibition, but also as the גמרא Gemara points out,
the prohibition is even on the borrower, not only on the lender.
So clearly this is a prohibition of a different sort. It is
not stealing money in the same way. And actually we've left, I
believe we ruled that the lender does have to give back the
money but the children certainly do not, that's agreed upon. It's interesting
actually that the שלחן ערוך, Shulchan Aruch, you know, has the laws
of ריבית Ribbis in,
not in חושן משפט, Choshen Mishpat, but in יורה דעה. Yoreh Deah.
So that is interesting, right? It's not in laws about money, it's
actually in laws of יורה דעה Yoreh Deah which is general laws
about like just general ritual prohibitions as it were. So anyway, interesting
question about how to think about it, but at least the גמרא
Gemara in the beginning did try to put it all in the
framework of, or at least compare it to, general prohibitions about לא
תגזול. lo sigzoil. Okay. Anyway, then we're getting on to that, now
we're sort of zooming in and focusing on rabbinic forms of ריבית
Ribbis which are going to be the most common of our focus.
Cases where you're not even necessarily intending to make extra money, but
it might work out that way, or the reverse, cases where you
are intending to make extra money but you're doing it in a
way that might be a little bit of a subterfuge to allow
you to charge interest. So an example of the second, the גמרא
Gemara said actually was quite ingenious, was somebody comes to you and
says, 'I want to borrow $100.' You say, 'Look buddy, I can't
lend you $100, but you know, but I have my iPhone here
to sell you for like, I always go with my iPhone, I
have my iPhone here to sell you for $100. I'll tell you
what,
I'll sell you my iPhone,' so
and you'll owe me $100. So you say okay fine. So sell
you the iPhone, you let me the $100 anyway. And then you
say, 'You know what? Actually I need that iPhone. I'll tell you
what, I'll buy it back from you for 90 bucks.' So I
buy it back from 90 bucks. So now I've basically, I basically
lent the guy, how does that work? Did I do that too
quickly? I lent the guy 90 bucks but he owes me 100
from the initial sale. Okay, so I lent him 90 and he's
going to pay me back 100 but it worked out as actually
a two, like it was a sale, a double sale with a
wink and a nod. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara says that that's prohibited
rabbinically. Okay, that was a case where clearly you were trying to
lend with interest and you did it through a subterfuge of a
sale. But often we have the reverse. They're actually trying to do
a sale, but the end result is that you wind up essentially
putting out money and getting back more money, and it looks like
interest. And how much is that a rabbinic problem? And particularly the
cases that the גמרא Gemara is focusing on is that I go
ahead and apparently this was a regular thing, that I would go
to people during the time when, you know, the grain was just
sort of like coming to market, but it was not yet the
height of the season, and I'd go to a person who sells
grain and I pay him well, you know, the current market rate
is whatever it is, $10 a bushel, you know, or $10 whatever
it is a pound. And I basically agree to him over the
course of the year that he's going to supply me with 100
pounds and I give him $1,000. Okay. And then what happens though
is, and it seems like it was this, it's not clear, but
it seems like it was reasonably likely that as the year would
proceed the prices would go up, but it does also seem that
it's possible that they would go down. Anyway, so as the year
proceeds and the prices are now going up, he's still paying me
at the rate of $10 a pound even though... now they're going
for twelve dollars a pound so I'm still getting a hundred pounds
for my thousand dollars even though I'm getting stuff that's actually worth
more than that but that's okay because at the time I did
it it was actually the established rate and the חידוש Chiddush is
if he actually had the flour and I paid him the money
it's not much of a חידוש Chiddush I actually just bought the
flour in his possession but the חידוש Chiddush is that even if
he has the flour and I didn't pay him the even if
he doesn't have the flour and I paid him the money that
works because in theory since now there's a regular market for it
and the price is fixed he can turn around and use that
money to buy the flour that he's going to then have to
supply me with during the course of the year so even though
I gave him money and he had no flour and at the
end of so you could think it wasn't really more of a
so much of a sale it was really more of a loan
you know whatever happened to אין אדם מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם
Ein adam makneh davar shelo ba l'olam type of a thing nevertheless
we consider it a you know and if it's more of a
loan and then he pays me back later something worth twelve hundred
dollars I lent him a thousand and I got back twelve hundred
that should be a problem but nevertheless we basically say that it
is a type of a sale even though by the way also
not only does he not have the money in his possession not
only does he not have the flour in his possession but also
מעות אינן קונות maos einan konos right you need משיכה meshicha but
we sort of gloss over those two things we say at least
rabbinically מעות הן קונות maos hen konos because you know you get
a מי שפרע Mi Shepara they're somewhat קונה koneh even though he
doesn't have the stuff in his possession actually רמב"ם Rambam says that
the idea of אין אדם מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם ein adam
makneh davar shelo ba l'olam doesn't apply presumably gets it from this
גמרא Gemara doesn't apply if the stuff is readily available in the
marketplace very important in terms of buying and selling futures that if
there's a ready market for something even though you don't have it
in your possession that's not a problem of selling something שלא בא
לעולם shelo ba l'olam because you could just turn around and buy
it immediately so we view it as a type of a sale
even though he doesn't have the stuff in his possession even though
it's only money that changed hands and then he can go ahead
and provide it during the rest of the year even though the
what do you call it even though the prices are now worth
more okay so that's basically a case like a מוכר באמנה mocher
b'amna you know somebody selling on trust or you know to be
provided for the rest of the year the question that the גמרא
Gemara is dealing with is what about if I don't actually give
him money I just actually say that hundred dollars by the way
that you owe me I am giving you back that hundred dollars
you owe me and now you can or that thousand dollars and
now you can provide me with a hundred pounds of flour so
I didn't actually give him money I just actually bought the flour
which he may or may not have you know with a loan
is that enough of a type of a purchase and a transaction
that now he can pay me back later in the year even
though it's going to might be worth more than a thousand dollars
when he pays it back to me over the course of the
year so the גמרא Gemara initially said that you can't do that
under any circumstances but now what the גמרא Gemara is sort of
honing in on is the possibility that you can do that as
long as he actually has the flour so again if I'm actually
giving him the money and he can take the cash and turn
it around and buy it from somebody else he doesn't have to
have the flour that's allowed we see that as a type of
a sale even if he doesn't have the flour if I don't
give him the money I just sort of give him back a
loan so it's less of a transaction it's more of a loan
I allow him to keep the money he owes me that we're
about to say will be allowed if he actually has the flour
in his possession then the fact that he has the flour in
his possession is enough to make it a type of a sale
even though I'm not really giving him money right now okay so
those are the cases that we're dealing with and that's what we're
going to now introduce as a way of explaining our משנה Mishna
because we have a very complicated משנה Mishna that seems to deal
with a case of rabbinic רבית ribbit or interest without being clear
what the problem in the משנה Mishna is so it deals with
flour and then trading it in for wine and whatever and it's
not exactly clear what the problem is and somehow it had to
do with the fact that he didn't have wine in his possession
made it a problem so the גמרא Gemara is now going to
tell us how to read that משנה Mishna based on the background
I just gave you so let's take a look אלא אמר רבא
Ella amar Rava two lines from the bottom of ס"ב עמוד ב'
Samech-Bet Amud Bet רבא Rava says כי שכיבנא Ki shachivna when I
die רבי אושעיא נפק לאפאי Rabbi Oshaya nafik l'afati when I go
up to heaven Rabbi Oshaya is going to come out to greet
me Rabbi Oshaya was one of the editors of the תוספתא Tosefta
he's going to come out and greet me when I die דמתרצנא
מתניתין כוותיה D'matritzna masnisin k'voseih
because I explain difficult משניות mishnayos according to the תוספתא Tosefta I
use the תוספתא Tosefta as my way of explaining difficult משניות mishnayos
rather than it's not just here that he's doing that he actually
says this a number of times because I regularly love the תוספתא
Tosefta of רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya and I use them to explain
difficult משניות mishnayos and he's going to come and welcome me with
open arms when I go up to heaven and I die okay
so how am I going to now use his תוספתא Tosefta to
explain our משנה Mishna דתני רבי אושעיא D'tani Rabbi Oshaya
here's the case that Rabbi Oshaya describes and now we're going to
say this is the case of our משנה Mishna הרי הנושה בחברו
מנה Harei ha'nosheh b'chavero maneh okay
Michael owed me a hundred dollars והלך ואמר על גורנו v'halach v'amar
al gorno
and I went to Michael and I went by his threshing floor
there at the time when the grain Grain was just beginning to
come to market. ואמר תן לי מעותיי, Ve-amar ten li me'osai,
Michael, where's the hundred dollars you owe me? שאני רוצה ליקח בהן
חטים. She-ani rotzeh likach bahen chittin. It's now the time, it's the
best. The wheat is just getting sold, it's the low market prices.
I need that hundred dollars right now so I can go ahead
and buy the wheat right now at the low cost of the
season. Okay? ואמר לו, Ve-amar lo, now Michael says to me, you
know what, Dove, I don't have the hundred dollars on me, but
you know what I do have? חטים יש לי. Chittin yesh li.
I do have actually the wheat that you're interested in buying. So
שאני נותן לך, She-ani noten lekha, and I'm prepared to give it
to you, to sell it to you, צא ועשה לי כשער של
עכשיו. Tze ve-aseh li ke-sha'ar shel akhshav. Let's look at the current,
you know, current costs. It's now going at ten dollars a pound.
Okay. Oh, fine. You wanted to buy, you want your cash now
so you can buy ten pounds of flour? I'll sell you those
tons, I'll owe you those ten pounds of flour instead of the
hundred dollars that I owe you. Instead of the hundred dollars, you'll
buy, you'll use that hundred dollars that I owe you, we'll use
that to buy ten pounds of flour so you don't have to
go to somebody else with the money to contract out ten pounds
of flour for the rest of the year for this hundred dollars.
You'll contract it out with me. You'll give me the hundred dollars
and I'll owe you the ten pounds of flour.
Well, I have to, you know, give it to you, right?
No, no, no.
But חטים יש לי. Chittin yesh li.
Yes, yes, yes. But the point is, the general contract here is
that you make the deal now to be provided over the course
of the year.
Oh, that's what we had then.
I understand. Yesterday. It's exactly what you had yesterday.
I, but that's, okay. You're right. It could be to give now,
but it seems very clearly that the case is to be provided
over the course of the year. I understand. Right. So this is
what Rabbi Oshaya is going to say yesterday, he said yesterday. Okay.
Okay, now, so fine, I made the deal with Michael, might as
well. He said he's going to give it to me. Why? So
he didn't have the hundred dollars, but I bought it off of
him for the hundred dollars. Okay. צא ועשה לי כשער של עכשיו.
Tze ve-aseh li ke-sha'ar shel akhshav. הגיע זמן חטים למכור. Higa zman
chittin limkor. Now comes the time for me to actually turn around
and take collection of that. Now it's the height of the season
and I can actually get, you know, get the best price for
it. So now I want to take possession of the flour that
I bought, the wheat that I bought a month ago and turn
around and sell it and make a profit. Now it's worth a
hundred and twenty dollars. Okay. So now I go to Michael and
I want to finally collect my wheat.
הגיע זמן חטים למכור. Higa zman chittin limkor. אמר לו תן לי
חטים שאני רוצה למכור וליקח בהן יין. Amar lo ten li chittin
she-ani rotzeh limkor ve-likach bahen yayin. Michael,
sell me now the wheat. I can now sell for a hundred
dollars, make a tidy twenty dollar profit, and now what I'm going
to do is turn around and use it to buy wine. And
the wine now is just has is just coming to market and
now I can get wine at the low point of the season
and make a profit with that. I'm a good businessman. Okay.
ואמר לו, Ve-amar lo, Michael of course says to me, okay, יש
לי חטים. Yesh li chittin. You know what? יש לי יין. Yesh
li yayin. You know, Michael says, I don't have the wheat to
give you right now, Dove, but I know it's worth a hundred
and twenty dollars, the ten bushels that you bought. So tell you
what, for the hundred and twenty dollars that you could sell it
for, you can buy a hundred and twenty dollars of wine off
of me and I'll provide it for you over the course of
the year. יש לי יין שאני נותן לך צא ועשה לי כשער
של עכשיו. Yesh li yayin she-ani noten lekha tze ve-aseh li ke-sha'ar
shel akhshav. Let's figure out now what the cost of wine is
and it's at the low point now and you'll get it really
cheap. Okay, fine. So that hundred and twenty dollars of wheat that
you should have given me, we're going to turn that into a
hundred and twenty dollars of wine now at the low point of
the season. כשער של
עכשיו. Ke-sha'ar shel akhshav. הגיע זמן יין למכור.
Higa zman yayin limkor.
All started with a loan of a hundred dollars. הגיע זמן יין
למכור. Higa zman yayin limkor. Now it's time for the wine to
be sold. And now that's, now I can make a good twenty
dollars of profit off of that. Okay. If you were to give
me the what we contracted earlier. Okay. אמר לו תן לי יין
שאני רוצה למכרו וליקח בהן שמן. Amar lo ten li yayin she-ani
rotzeh le-mokhran ve-likach bahen shemen. I want to take that, take that
profit, sell the wine and now use it to buy oil. Oil
is now at the low point of the season. Wow, I am
a good businessman. ואמר לו שמן יש לי שאני נותן לך. Ve-amar
lo shemen yesh li she-ani noten lekha. You know what? I don't
have the wine, but I do have oil. So I know the
wine now you could sell for a hundred and forty. I'll owe
you a hundred and forty dollars worth of oil. שאני נותן לך
צא ועשה לי כשער של עכשיו. She-ani noten lekha tze ve-aseh li
ke-sha'ar shel akhshav.
So go ahead and figure it out now and I'll owe you
a hundred and forty dollars worth of oil. Okay. Now, and then
in the end of the day you will pay me hopefully eventually
you'll have something to give me and you'll give me back a
hundred and forty dollars worth of oil and it all started with
the fact that you owed me a hundred dollars. Right? You owed
me a hundred dollars, I used a hundred dollars to buy the
wheat, to buy the wine, to buy the oil, so חד גדיא.
Chad Gadya. Anyway, and in the end because of a hundred dollars
you owed, you're paying me back a hundred and forty dollars worth
of oil. And then there's really another question: are you paying me
back just in oil or are you actually going to say, you
know what, I don't have the oil on me but I'll give
you back a hundred and forty in cash or a hundred and
sixty in cash because then the oil went up actually when I
come to collect the oil? So that looks like ריבית. ribbis. Is
that allowed? One minute. So it says
כולם, kullam, all of these, אם יש לו מותר. im yesh lo
mutar. If Michael actually had the wheat on him when he agreed
to give and to provide me the wheat and then he had
the wine when he agreed to provide me the wine and all
those, it's permissible. אין לו אסור. Ein lo assur. And if he
doesn't, it's forbidden. Okay, why? Because yesterday we said that if I
actually gave Michael cash, you know, he could go ahead and sell
me to provide the wheat later even if he didn't have the
wheat on him since the market of wheat was now, the price
was fixed and the wheat was available. But what we also said
yesterday, as Michael correctly pointed out, was that if I don't give
him cash now, if I just try to buy it based on
money he owes me, it doesn't work even if he has the
wheat in his possession. That was the ברייתא braitah we taught yesterday.
This ברייתא braitah of רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya teaches differently. This ברייתא
braitah of רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya says as long as he has
the stuff in his possession, even if I don't actually pay him
any money now, I'm only paying him with some money he owes
me, and then I'm repaying him with the wheat for the wine
and the wine for whatever etc. etc. No money's ever changing hands
at that time. Since as long as he has the object he's
selling, the produce he's selling in possession, that also is enough to
make it seem as a sale, not a type of loan, and
make it permissible. Okay, so well yesterday we said it wasn't allowed
unless money changes hands. Here we are saying according, right, that's what
you asked me a minute ago. Here we are saying that was
רבי חייא Rabbi Hiyya yesterday, this is רבי אושעיא. Rabbi Oshaya. Here
we are saying that it is allowed as long as he has
the stuff in his possession. And that explains the משנה. mishna. Because
the משנה, mishna, if you remember, had a case where somebody where
did Michael write the משנה mishna up on the board? Where's the
משנה, mishna, Michael? Okay. So the case of the משנה mishna was,
okay, so he bought חטים chittin for twenty-five, and that was the
שער, shaar, and then it was then it was thirty. So that
was like the case, right, which is that that
well basically I made a profit there, you know Michael now has
I bought it for twenty-five and now I want to take thirty
as the profit, okay, and then and I say you know what,
give me my give me these give me and I say to
Michael, give me the wheat, right? Remember, he owed me the money.
Okay, we're going to explain the משנה mishna just like the ברייתא.
braitah. Michael owed me twenty-five, okay, and I said you know what
Michael, instead of giving me the twenty-five or Michael said to me
I don't have the twenty-five but I'll sell you a כור kor
of grain. Okay, so instead of he owed me twenty-five, right, worth
twenty-five. No, initially it was worth twenty-five. Then it came time for
me to collect the grain and it was worth thirty. And then
I said Michael, give me the grain that you owe me. And
Michael said you know what, I don't have the grain but instead
I'll give you wine. Okay, now all of that would be fine
according to רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya provided that what? He has the
wine. So it says והיין ve'hayayin he says והב לי יין, vehav
li yayin, ויין אין לו. veyayin ein lo.
So because he doesn't have the wine, that's what made it forbidden.
Okay, because I am buying it off of him, he's going to
provide it for me later, later it'll probably be worth more. That
would all be fine if either number one, I gave him the
cash or number two, if I didn't give him the cash because
he owed it to me and I let him keep what he
owed me, it would be fine if he had the produce. But
because he doesn't have the produce, that's why it's forbidden. So we're
going to explain this משנה mishna based on רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya
that it would be okay to do if he had the produce,
but not okay if he doesn't. I will take the questions, I
need one more line in the גמרא. Gemara. ומאי לקח? Umai lakach?
So according to this, what does it mean that he purchased? Because
we said that as long as money changed hands initially, it's all
okay. So the גמרא Gemara says what does it mean purchased? You're
saying that as long as it changed hands it's all okay. It
means לקח בהלוואתו. lakach behalvato. It means it means that you purchased
with the money owed you, but the reason this whole thing is
a problem is because money never changed hands in the context of
a sale. That the initial purchasing of the wheat occurred through giving
you credit. Now רש"י Rashi by the way says you don't even
have to really say that. Because רש"י Rashi says even if the
initial wheat came through giving Michael money and therefore this was okay
even if you didn't have the wheat, when it came time to
convert it into wine, at that stage it was a loan. At
that stage no money changed hands, right? So even if this was
okay, I could buy the wheat from Michael even if he doesn't
have it because money changed hands, Michael now owes me the wheat,
right? That was okay because the you know wheat could have been
bought whatever, but he now what he does is he owes me
I bought the wheat, he owes me the wheat. Now when I
come to say keep the wheat, give me wine, that is a
new transaction where no money changed hands. And in that transaction, it's
only legitimate if Michael has the wine. He felt okay. So rightfully
רש"י Rashi says you don't have to change the word here because
the key is that the wine was the problematic transaction. Bottom line
is, in order to make a sale of future stuff good, you
need one of two. Either you need what I need is new
markers.
What if you loan me a marker, we'll do swap-a-swap. To make
a transaction good you
either need money to change
hands, that's called איסרו בא לידו, issaro ba le-yado, which is funny
because איסר, issar, it's an איסר, issar, it's not the forbidden thing,
but איסרו בא לידו, issaro ba le-yado, so that's a confusing phrase.
Or
you have to be current you have to be currently in. In
possession
of merchandise.
So יצא השער yatza hasha'ar makes no difference.
Yeah, well no, you also need יצא השער, yatza hasha'ar, okay? It
starts that you need יצא השער, yatza hasha'ar, we'll see about that
later. You need it to be that there's now a fixed price
has been established and it's readily available in the marketplace, but even
with יצא השער, yatza hasha'ar, it's only going to be good if
either money changes hands or you're in possession of the merchandise. Yes,
go.
So here's my question. This whole thing is like fascinating.
It's like, it's sort of like the way the real estate market
crashed with the bundled mortgages. There was nothing there backing any of
it up. It was just ideas back and forth. Right. So when
I think Michael you said this was credit, it's an issue of
credit, so there has to be something backing it up.
Right. That's a good point, it's like the underlying equity
here, right, the underlying equity, the liquid equity in some form
when you're buying on credit.
Right, but my question is though, in what sense is this ריבית?
ribbit?
Like I keep
hearing
this is a mess economically, but why is it interest there? Why
is it an issue of ריבית? ribbit?
Because it's not, it's merchandise is, is, one minute. It's because that's
why you have to learn about אבק ריבית avak ribbis rather... hold
on, available...
I know. You were going to get like most things we're going
to get to it not by starting conceptually and then developing the
cases, we're going to start by the concrete and work backwards. The
reason it's not real ריבית, ribbis, that's why it's דרבנן derabbanan ריבית,
ribbis, but it's because basically if I give you a hundred dollars
and two months later when I come to collect you give me
something worth, if at the time I went into a store and
it's now you know Cyber Monday or Black Friday or whatever it
is and I give you a hundred dollars and you give me
something worth two hundred dollars or a hundred forty dollars, it's just
you know a bargain, I made a good buy. Right, but if
I give you a hundred dollars and you wait two months and
you deliver something worth a hundred and forty, then that could be
seen of as a type of because and here's a key phrase,
here's a key phrase that we're going to come to at the
end of today's דף, daf, אגר נטר, agar natar, which is Aramaic
which means שכר sechar
and
המתנת hamtanat like המתנת hamtanat המתנת המעות. hamtanat hama'ot. If you're giving
me money because you did not pay me right away, then that
is seen as a type of ריבית. ribbis. I give you a
hundred dollars, you got to hold on to it for two months
and then you paid me a hundred and ten. The fact that
you got to hold on to it for time and you did
not give me the exchange immediately, even if it is a purchase
and not a loan, it's more like a loan because we didn't
exchange things immediately. And then when you gave me back my side
of what I was getting for my money, you gave me back
something worth more than my money. Okay, so if I buy something
for a hundred dollars and you deliver it in two months and
it's worth a hundred and twenty, then that basically looks more like
a loan and less like a sale. That because you didn't deliver
it right away and you had two months to deliver, you actually
gave me an extra twenty dollars worth of merchandise. So even though
you're giving me merchandise and I gave you money and that makes
it a sale and it was a sale, it looks like ריבית
ribbis because the exchange, what I got came later and was worth
more than what I gave. Okay, so therefore in these cases, in
these cases, if now it would be I paid money and the
price was a low you know rate and when you came to
pay me to give me the merchandise it was worth more. So
that would look like ריבית ribbis because you were able to hold
on to it. But because and this is actually if you want
to say the חידוש, chiddush, once I point out that that's a
problem, it's a חידוש chiddush that this is מותר. mutar. But because
actual money changed hands and there was יצא השער, yatza hasha'ar, you
could easily have just turned around, went to the market, bought me
that stuff and given it to me, then that makes it as
if, okay, it was totally in my capability to hand it to
you right now. And therefore it's not like you're lending me money
and because I can't give it to you and because I need
to use it for a certain amount of time, right, the fact
that I could have easily converted it and given it to you
makes it as not המתנת המעות, hamtanat hama'ot, just the fact that
no, the rates went up. Okay, or similarly if you're in possession
of the merchandise, even though you don't give me the money, you
let me keep a loan, right, but since I could just give
you the merchandise, again that makes it enough of a sale that
it's not like because you're letting me hold extend the loan. Yes.
The answer to my question is in the passing of that time,
what was a sale, what was structured as a sale has the
appearance over time as having been structured as a loan.
That is the concern. Or right, either having been structured as a
loan or look, ריבית ribbis is a problem even if nobody questions
that it was structured that way, even if as long as it
just has the effect, like if basically you lent me a hundred
dollars and I And I gave you back a hundred dollars and
we made absolutely no agreement at the time. And after I gave
you back a hundred dollars I said דב, Dov, I really want
to thank you for lending me that money at a crucial time.
Here's an extra twenty bucks. Okay, that's called ריבית מאוחרת. Ribbis Meucharess.
It was never any part of the arrangement, but nevertheless it's also
a problem rabbinically because you got more than you gave. So I
would agree with you except except I just wouldn't limit it to
say that it looks like it was structured as such. But yes,
it has elements of ריבית Ribbis because since the stuff was it
had because those ways in which it had right, it has the
it be money the what was given back was not given back
the exchange did not occur right away, when it did occur it
was for more value than was taken.
So that's enough to go by.
I mean, you know, nothing, a day, whatever. I mean I don't
know if there's any time at all. Yeah.
Is this equally problematic if price goes down because that's לווה על
לווה? Lo'ave al Lo'ave? No.
Well, no, if the price goes the לווה על הלווה Lo'ave al
HaLo'ave is when it is ריבית. Ribbis. If the price goes down
then it's not ריבית, Ribbis, then you gave back less than you
gave. So you're thinking more of אונאה, Ona'ah, you know, it could
be like with אונאה Ona'ah would it matter if it went up
or went down if the issue is one side is being cheated.
But it's not ריבית Ribbis unless the side that is giving the
money is getting back more than he took. If the guy giving
the money is getting back less than he gave, it's not ריבית
Ribbis at all. If I gave you a hundred dollars and you
gave me ninety-five dollars' worth of product, there's no ריבית. Ribbis.
The איסור Issur on the לווה Lo'ave is not to underpay the
מלווה. Malveh. The איסור Issur on the לווה Lo'ave is to overpay
the מלווה. Malveh. The איסור Issur on the לווה Lo'ave is to
pay interest. It's not like אונאה. Ona'ah. By אונאה, Ona'ah, the איסור
Issur is on the seller to overcharge and on the buyer to
underbuy. Here the prohibition is on the מלווה Malveh and the לווה
Lo'ave to pay interest, to charge and pay interest. If what's given
back is less than what was taken, nobody transgresses. Yes.
Is the problem is am I earning money from my money? Right.
Does it appear like I'm earning...
Well, you can earn money from your money, you can invest in
a business, which is how the whole היתר עסקה Hetter Iska works.
There's no problem of having your money work for you, you know
what I mean? The problem is
that when it appears to be, right, a loan and not a
sale. Okay.
If I invested in a business it's just loaning the money.
No,
you buy a portion of the business.
And then but then you also assume part of the risk.
Right. So the less that there's an assumption of risk, the more
it's a loan. But the problem isn't having your money work for
you, right? So you could say if my money is protected and
it's working for me, that makes it like a loan, then I
would agree. But again it's not I would not conceptualize it as
having your money earn money for you. Yes.
All my money got together and made little baby moneys. Yes.
Where does the category of giving a gift for appreciation fit in,
like when you said here's 20. Right.
Right, so that's an interesting question, like ריבית דברים. Ribbis Devarim. Like
am I allowed to even say thank you when I give you
back the money or whatever? So we'll get to that. Okay.
All
right, yes.
But if it's a transaction, if you're
buying it now for whatever the crop is going to be worth
when it's developed,
aren't you
rather than doing it as a loan, isn't it sort of an
assumption of risk? I want to lock in today's price and if
there's a drought I'll end up doing worse, but absolutely.
Well actually a drought you'll probably do better because the money the
value will go up. But anyway, the opposite, whatever. Yes, absolutely. And
that's why it is allowed as long as there's one element that
makes it enough like a sale. As long as either money changes
hands or the other side is in possession. But if neither money
changes hands and the side isn't in possession, then
it all looks like you're playing the market and there's no real
sale going on here and then it looks a little bit too
fishy. All right, let's go on. By the way an interesting side
point that רש"י Rashi says, רש"י Rashi says when you buy it
with a loan and not with actually changing hands, רש"י Rashi says
it actually the other side would get a מי שפרע Mi Sheparay
they would either side would get a מי שפרע Mi Sheparay if
they back out. That the idea that מעות קונות, Maos Konos, you
know, מדאורייתא, Midioraisa, whatever מדרבנן, Midrabbanan, you get a מי שפרע. Mi
Sheparay. רש"י Rashi says it's even if money doesn't change hands, even
if you're buying something just by letting somebody keep the money that
they owe you. Other ראשונים Rishonim disagree. So going back to issues
of the previous פרק, Perek, okay, that's interesting. The reason רש"י Rashi
says this works when you buy it with a loan is that
he says that's still a type of a מי שפרע Mi Sheparay
even though no money changed hands.
How do you translate what does it say about that box on
the top, שכר המתנת מעות? Schar Hamtanas Maos?
Oh that because I spelled מעות Maos with a ט Tes when
I should have spelled it with a
ת. Tav.
Okay,
מעות. Maos. Okay.
Just a reminder the first year I went to ישראל Yisrael right
out of high school for my year in ישראל Yisrael and I
had all the עברית Ivris I knew was from learning גמרא. Gemara.
So anyways I wanted to ask somebody if they have, can they
change my money or whatever? So I was saying יש לך ממון
*yesh lecha mamon*? מעות *ma'ot*?
It was a little funny. Anyway, alright, let's go on.
What? Some cat's talking on the street, he's like Elon?
Elon,
right, exactly.
Alright, let's go on. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this:
Okay, okay. Okay, ומהי לקא אמר רבא Amar Rava, *u'mai laka amar
Rava*, שמע מינא מדרבי אושעיא *shema mina mid'Rabbi Oshaya*, תלת *tlat*, three
things. שמע מינא דמעמידין מלווה על גבי פירות peiros, *shema mina d'ma'amidin
milve al gabi perot*, ושמע מינא דלא כי סרבה לידיהו *u'shema mina
d'lo ki sarba l'yadeihu*. This is very helpful. Rava now spelling it
out, that basically you can actually give the guy back the money
he owes you as a way of buying this fruit and paying
off the fruit later and it's not like a problem that the
money did not change hands. It's true the money didn't change hands,
but that doesn't mean it can't be done, it could be done
as long as ושמע מינה הוא דיש לו *u'shema mina hu d'yesh
lo*, as long as the guy has possession of the merchandise. Okay,
he's just spelling out what we just wrote on the board. It's
very nice. You can do it through a loan by giving back
the loan as long as the guy has possession of the merchandise.
ושמע מינא איתא לדרבי ינאי *u'shema mina ita l'd'Rabbi Yannai*, and we
also hold that we hold like Rabbi Yannai. Who's Rabbi Yannai? דאמר
de'amar רבי ינאי מה לי הן מה לי דמיהן ma li hen
ma li dameihen, *d'amar Rabbi Yannai ma li hen ma li dmeihen*.
What do I care about them? What do I care about their
money? Okay, now what does that mean? That means that, hold on,
let me just check רש״י *Rashi* for one second.
Yes, the fact that basically when I go and I say, 'Oh,
give me my wheat' and you say, 'Oh, I don't have wheat,
but the wheat is worth 30, I'll sell you the wine I've
got for 30'. Okay, we understand that the person can actually pay
that because he's treating the wheat he owes me as the thirty
dollars of its value, and then I'm buying the wine with the
thirty dollars value of the wheat, that when it comes time to
give something, you can say, 'Well, what difference does it make if
you give the thing or if you give its value?' So the
same way, the reason I'm allowed to buy thirty dollars worth of
wine here even though he owes me wheat, right, is because I
can just convert that wheat into its value and then buy the
wine with the money he owes me. מה לי הן מה לי
דמיהן mah li hen mah li dmeihen, *ma li hen ma li
dmeihen*. What do I care about the thing or about the value,
it's all the same. Now how is that relevant? It's relevant for
the following case which is going to be, you'll see, really start
to sound a little bit like ריבית ribbis. *ribbit*.
Okay, yeah, so the first שמע מינא *shema mina* is מעמידין מלווה
על גבי פירות peiros. *ma'amidin milve al gabi perot*, like the loan
itself or the money?
No, I think it means מלווה *malveh*, the creditor. The creditor comes
to the threshing floor and says, 'You know, okay, go ahead and
give me your...
take the wheat.'
Right, exactly. Okay, דאימר *d'eimar*, Rava, I believe so. דאימר רבא Rava
אמר amar... עושין אמנה בפירות אין עושין אמנה בדמים *d'eimar Rava amar
osin amana b'perot ein osin amana b'damim*. Okay, this is called אמנה
*amana* where I basically, you buy it for me for like futures,
but you know, and I'm going to provide it during the course
of the year. You can do it if what you're doing is
if the guy in the end pays you back the thing that...
I give you a thousand dollars for a hundred bushels of wheat,
that's the price now, and when you're going to pay back to
me later in the year, even though in the year a hundred
bushels might be worth more. That you can do, you can pay
me back a hundred bushels later in the year. Okay, ואין עושין
אמנה בדמים *v'ein osin amana b'damim*, but let's say when it came
time to pay me back the hundred bushels of wheat, you said,
'Look, I don't have a hundred bushels anymore, but I know the
price now is twelve dollars a bushel, here, I'll give you twelve
hundred dollars.' So Rava says you can't do that. I gave you
a thousand dollars. Two months later you're giving me twelve hundred dollars
in cash. That really looks like a loan, yes, hidden behind the
scenes. It was because I bought wheat and then you, rather than
giving me wheat, gave me back the value of the wheat. But
in terms of what actually happened, I handed over a thousand dollars
in cash, two months later you handed over twelve hundred dollars in
cash. Okay, so that doesn't work, even though what it's actually representing
is the wheat that you owe me. Rava says you can't do
that.
How's the grain money often treated? פירות peiros *perot* or is it...?
Oh, that's an interesting question. I don't know, I don't know, but
I don't want to get distracted but that's an interesting question. Okay,
רבי ינאי אמר לא מה לי הן מה לי דמיהן mah li
hen mah li dmeihen. *Rabbi Yannai amar lo ma li hen ma
li dmeihen*. No, what do I care if you give them or
you give their money? The reality is it works, you bought wheat,
the guy was supposed to deliver wheat. This is actually how the
futures market works, right? Like you buy a futures, like you can
actually take collection in the commodity, okay, but most of the time
nobody ever does that, right? So anyway, I actually, the guy actually
owed me the wheat, okay, and that would have been okay because,
you know, I bought it, my money changed hands, it was ושער
יצא *v'sha'ar yatza*, he could have, you know, the wheat was available.
So when he comes time to pay, well pay me in the
money. If you could pay me in the wheat, you could pay
me in the money. מה לי הן מה לי דמיהן mah li
hen mah li dmeihen, *ma li hen ma li dmeihen*. Okay, so
that's consistent with the idea here that we were able to convert
the wheat into dollars and buy with that wine. Now it's a
little bit of a bigger חידוש chiddush, *chiddush*, because here at least
at the end of the day, you're not actually taking possession of
cash, but when you gave cash and took possession of more cash,
it looks a lot more like ריבית ribbis, *ribbit*. Okay, here conceptually
you converted it into the 30 and you bought more wine with
it, but you didn't actually take possession of the cash. Okay, but
that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying, that that's implicit in
what you did over here. So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
מיתיבי Meisev, *meitivei*, I'll ask on Rava. How could רב Rav, say
what he does? We have this ברייתא, braisa, we have this reading
that that's exactly what you did. You did convert it into cash.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this, מיתיבי, כולם אם יש לו
מותר. kulam im yesh lo mutar. We said you can do this
whole transaction if he has it, even if, you know, he's converting
the wheat into wine, and the wine into oil, and he's essentially
paying you back with cash, not with the product itself. So that
seems to prove like רב ינאי Rav Yanai that that's okay. So
the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב הונא אמר רב, Amar Rav Huna
amar Rav, כשמשך. b'shemashach. No, no, no. That case is okay because
you didn't actually directly say, okay, the wheat will be worth the
thirty dollars and I'll buy the wine. You actually took possession of
the wheat.
Okay, there's no, you didn't get the value in cash.
You actually got it in the wheat and then you gave back
the wheat and you took the wine. Problem is that that's not
פשט. pshat. The whole פשט pshat in all these cases is that
he doesn't have the product to deliver. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
is going to say, okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, but first
it's answering, no, no, in all these cases you actually did take
the wheat itself. Then there's very little חידוש, chiddush and you actually
just did a transaction, you just bought an object. What's the חידוש
of the whole thing? So the גמרא Gemara says,
what?
I thought the whole point was that he didn't have it.
I know. So that's what the גמרא Gemara is essentially going to
say back. Okay, or no, he had it at the time he
agreed, but then he didn't have it at the time he was
supposed to pay. But the whole point is that it was never
a real sale. It was always a sale that had not yet
taken possession of the object, which is what the גמרא Gemara is
going to say back. Okay, so that's what the גמרא Gemara is
going to say back. Okay, the גמרא Gemara. says, אי בשמשך צריכא
למימר. ei b'shemashach tzaricha lemeimar. What? You wouldn't have to teach this
whole ברייתא braisa if the guy actually took possession of the product.
So, אלא כגון שיחד לו קרן זוית. ela k'gon she-yiched lo keren
zavis. Fine. It's not like he technically took possession, but it's as
if he took possession. He designated a corner. So basically you came,
I came and I told you, yeah, there's a hundred dollars that
I owe you, you know what? I'll give it to you in
wheat. Now remember we said I have the wheat, right? So you
didn't take possession, but I said that wheat, that's in that corner
over there, that's about twenty bushels or in that corner, that'll be
your wheat. Now you technically don't own it. You didn't do a
קנין משיכה. kinyan meshicha. You gave money, but that's again a partial
קנין kinyan is a מי שפרע. mi she-para. So it's so but
because I designated that, and then when you come back, you know,
two months later and say, okay, give me those twenty bushels, I'll
say, no, no, let me just give you wine instead, but because
it was somewhat like you had already quasi-taken possession, then it's more
allowed to say I'll just give you the money that those are
worth and we'll use that money to buy the wine. Okay, because
it's somewhat more like you took possession of it. So it's allowed
here, it's a hard read, but what we're saying is you're allowed
to convert it to money because it's as if it was already
my object. But if it was never as if it was my
object and I came to take possession and you said, no, no,
instead of giving you the wheat I'll just, it's worth a hundred
twenty dollars, I'll give you a hundred twenty dollars or I'll let
you buy a hundred twenty dollars worth of wine, right? In that
case, that would according to רב, Rav he would say that's more
like ריבית. ribbis You gave money, and then what was given back
even virtually given back was cash. But when what was given, it
was as if it was mine and then you're saying let me
give you a hundred twenty dollars, it's as if I already took
possession, so it's not like you're giving me back cash, in fact
you're paying me for the object that was mine. Yeah.
Is this a weak type of קנין kinyan like a קנין ייחוד?
kinyan yichud?
Yeah, yeah, but it's not relevant in other areas. Meaning in normal
מקח וממכר, mekach u-memkar, it's enough like you took possession, it appears
enough like you took possession that it makes it less that I'm
giving money and getting back more
and more money.
Okay, so yeah, yeah, that's what these two requirements are hitting at
a little bit, right?
That it has to be like more of a transaction, right?
It's just a little weird because then you get into questions of
like, okay, if it gets destroyed or something happens right in the
meantime, who's...
Right, well no, but that clearly it is not, it is
totally not yet owned by the other party. It's right, it's not
yet the sale is not right, exactly. The sale is not final,
which is what makes it a little bit more like a loan,
right? That you don't yet own physically the object itself. So it
is a sale, but in some ways it's not a final sale,
that's what makes it more loan-like. Okay, but anyway but what we're
saying is that רב Rav says normally when you have to pay
back wheat, you cannot convert that into money. The reason here we're
allowing you to convert, I would have said the reason that we're
allowing you to convert it into money is at the end of
the day you don't actually hand over the cash. That makes it
more acceptable, but the גמרא is saying actually also because to some
degree you had already taken quasi-possession of the wheat itself. Okay, so
now the גמרא says like this.
Okay, so
ושמואל אמר הא מני רבי יהודה היא. v'Shmuel amar ha-mani Rabbi Yehuda
hi. No, no, no. This idea that you can convert it into
cash and it's okay,
right, is implied here that you can convert it into cash and
even in the more extreme case, which is I borrowed money, I
not borrowed, I took in money to buy wheat and then in
the end rather than giving you wheat I gave back more money,
which really looks like ריבית, ribbis although the wheat was what it
was about, right, that idea that that's allowed, מה לי הן מה
לי דמיהן, that idea that is the The ברייתא braita doesn't prove
that רב is wrong because the ברייתא braita could be going like
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. הא מני רבי יהודה היא Ha manni Rabbi
Yehuda hi דאמר צד אחד בריבית מותר tzad echad b'ribbis mutar that
says if one side of a transaction would turn out to be
ריבית ribbis. but the other side would not, then it is permissible,
okay, which is a very extreme idea. What does that mean? דתניא
Detanya let's see the case. היה נושה בחברו מנה Haya nosheh b'chavero
maneh ועשה לו שדהו מכר. v'asah lo sadeh mecher. Okay, so basically
I go ahead here, David owes me a hundred dollars, and David
says and I say, "David, where's the money you owe me?" and
David says, "Look, Dov, I don't have the money. Tell you what
though, my field here is worth a hundred dollars. If I don't
pay you by the end of the month, you'll just take possession
of my field, okay?" The money I owe you you
now he wasn't initially that was part of the transaction that he
just owed me a hundred dollars, so he said that money that
I owe you, that hundred dollars I owe you, we'll use that
money to be a purchase price of this field on, if I
can't pay you it back to you by the end of the
month.
Okay, with a lien anyway?
No, or the lien would be more complicated because then it would
be part of the actual structuring of the loan. But this was
not part of the actual structuring of the loan. Not implicit? No,
I came to him, I lent him a hundred dollars. Oh, maybe,
but maybe, oh but then I'd have to go maybe through בית
דין beis din and here he's setting the price. Maybe maybe there
wasn't a שטר. shtar. Let's not worry about liens. No liens, okay.
Because but it's important because if it were through the structuring of
the loan, it would be more of a ריבית ribbis. issue. Here
it starts by a loan, okay? It's not like the field is
now in payment of the loan, that could make more problems. No,
he owes me a hundred dollars, he says, "I'll tell you what,
I will sell you my field for the hundred dollars I owe
you if I can't pay you back the hundred dollars by the
end of the month." Okay, so it's a sale, it is not
a collection of a loan per se. All right, so that's what
he says. All right, that's fine. But now בזמן שמוכר אוכל פירות,
Bizman shemmocher ochel peiros,
now what's happening during that month? Okay, if David is eating the
fruit during that month, so then מותר mutar of course it's permissible.
Then at the end of the month he doesn't pay, I collect,
I buy the field at the agreed-upon purchase price. שלום על ישראל.
Shalom al Yisrael.
However, בזמן שמלווה אוכל פירות bizman shemalveh ochel peiros
let's say during that month I am benefiting from the field, then
what's going to happen? Then at the end of the month let's
say David doesn't pay me the money. Fine, then it's great, then
I bought the field and it's mine. Now it's not exactly clear
here, are we saying that retroactively I own the field, he sold
it to me from today if he doesn't pay me in a
month? Let's assume that, it's not clear. Okay, but then it would
be perfect. He doesn't pay me the money, retroactively I owned it
as of today, I've been eating the fruit of my own field.
Wonderful, no big deal, okay. However, what will happen if he does
pay me the money at the end of the month? Okay, then
he paid me the money at the end of the month and
what did I do during the course of the month? I was
benefiting from the field. I lent him a hundred dollars, I got
back a hundred dollars, and over the course of a month I
benefited from the fruit of his field.
Well that's that retroactive idea like why were you benefiting?
Because on the presumption that one of us had a benefit and
since it was looking like he wasn't going to pay up or
whatever and I was assuming and hoping that it would become my
field, so that was just what we agreed upon. We agreed that
I would benefit during the course of that time. That according to
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is not allowed because if it turns out
that he pays me back the money, I got benefit from the
loan, okay? Otherwise it was just no, I just purchased a field,
okay? So the so אסור, assur, so that's forbidden. רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says, אמר רבי יהודה amar Rabbi Yehuda מותר. mutar. I'm sorry,
רבי יהודה אומר אף בזמן שמלווה אוכל פירות מותר. Rabbi Yehuda omer
af bizman shemalveh ochel peiros mutar. No, even that's allowed. Why? Presumably
this is צד אחד בריבית, tzad echad b'ribbis, meaning since it it
could wind up and actually תוספות Tosafos points out David can control
it that it could wind up that it would totally not have
any gain for me, that he would actually let me buy the
field, okay? Therefore the fact that it worked out in the other
way that he gave me back the money and I did gain
from a loan, that was not ריבית. ribbis It was not part
of the initial agreement, number one, that's important. It wasn't part of
the initial agreement. Okay, number two, it might be worth adding that
even though it started here with a loan there was an element
here of making it a sale, that's why I said it wasn't
it wasn't liens, it was a new thing defined as a sale
that piggybacked on a loan. So it started on a loan but
it was a sale. Number two, that's important, and and so it
was, it wasn't, it wasn't conditioned that way, it was a sale
and it was possible that it would have ended without me having
any gain, okay? But since it ended the other way with him
paying back the full amount and me having gain, that is not
considered to be ריבית. ribbis It wasn't part of the arrangement, there
was a context of a sale here, or at least a at
least a at least an offered sale, in the end it didn't
work out to be the sale, but at least a possible sale,
okay? And therefore it is not considered ריבית ribbis. according to רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. One minute, that's צד אחד בריבית tzad echad b'ribbis
meaning one way it worked out would have not been ריבית ribbis
had it been a sale, so even when it wasn't a sale
it's not considered
ריבית. ribbis אמר רבי יהודה Amar Rabbi Yehuda מעשה maiseh story בבייתוס
בן זונין. b'Beisus ben Zunin. This בבייתוס בן זונין, b'Beisus ben Zunin,
God bless him, he was involved in so many different business deals.
He provided so many good case studies for the גמרא. Okay, the
story was with בייתוס בן זונין Baisos ben Zonin שעשה שדהו מכר
על פי she-asa sadehu mechar al pi רבי אלעזר בן עזריה. Rabbi
Elazar ben Azariah. He did this case that he was prepared to
sell his field. Sounds like he was, it’s interesting, he usually is
rich so you would think he would be the one that would
be buying the field, but anyway sounds like here he was the
one that had borrowed the money and was going to sell his
field. Okay.
ולוקח אוכל פירות היה veloke'ach ochel peiros hayah and the purchaser ate
the fruit and that was totally allowed even though it was under
the auspices of רבי אלעזר בן עזריה. Rabbi Elazar ben Azariah. Okay,
even though it could have worked out that the guy was and
made money off of it. אמרו לו, Amru lo, so the Rabbis
objected, משם ראיה, mishom raya, you want to bring a proof from
there? מוכר אוכל פירות היה ולא לוקח, mochar ochel peiros hayah velo
loke'ach, you’ve got his facts wrong. That was a case of the
seller eating the fruit not the לוקח. loke'ach. So that’s why it
was okay. So מאי בינייהו, mai beineihu, what are they debating?
אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, צד אחד דריבית איכא בינייהו tzad echad d'ribbis
ika beineihu when something is ריבית ribbis. on one side of the
transaction. Okay, meaning not meaning that one way it could work out,
and again תוספות Tosafos points out that the sides can control which
way it works out, would be ריבית ribbis. and the other way
does not. That according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is not ריבית.
ribbis And again רש"י Rashi also points out that there’s a מכר
mechar component. Although ironically here the problematic case is when there’s no
מכר mechar component when you didn't opt for the sale. Okay, so
anyway so that would be why if, so going back to this
issue, why is it allowed to convert this into money? And even
more problematic, why would it be, why might, why would it be
allowed that I basically buy money, you give me cash, buy wheat,
and then rather than me giving you back wheat, I give you
back the cash for the wheat at a time when it’s worth
more? Right? That’s, remember that really looks problematic. So the answer is,
well, even if you say normally that's not allowed, I can explain
this ברייתא, beraisa, this משנה, mishna, whatever, that that's רבי יהודה. Rabbi
Yehuda. Since you have the option of giving back the fruit even
if you choose to give back the money, so yes it looks
like ריבית. ribbis. You got a hundred, you pay back
120, but that’s צד אחד בריבית tzad echad b'ribbis because you could
have given back the fruit. Okay. So therefore because according to רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda at least that would not be a problem.
Yeah, in the case of the field. So the נושה noshe and
the לוקח loke'ach are the same person. Right. So what’s interesting is
נושה noshe is the language of ריבית ribbis, and loan, and לוקח
loke'ach is the language of sale. Right. So even the language shifts,
that is correct,
to show the conflation exactly, fracturing of that moment in the transaction.
Exactly. Exactly. Okay, so רבא Rava said, now back to this debate
of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and the חכמים, Chachamim, this wouldn't necessarily
explain the earlier issue about converting it into money and why that
would be allowed, but רבא Rava says, "No, no, no. רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda is not as extreme as you think he is, he’s
not that lenient. ריבית על מנת להחזיר איכא בינייהו. ribbis al menas
lehachazir ika beineihu. Really when רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you can
go ahead with that deal and be לוקח אוכל פירות, loke'ach ochel
peiros, that’s only on the condition that if it winds up that
the guy paid back the loan and you didn't buy the field,
you have to give him back for the money for the fruit
that you ate. Okay, so it’s not so nice, it’s not as
easy as you think, oh look I’ll be taking a big bite,
that really looks problematic doesn't it? I mean you give him the
money and anyway, by the way you could imagine a very easy
הערמה ha'arama about that, right? You give him money and then you
do this and then oh I’ll buy it if whatever and then
you’re eating the פירות, you’re getting a lot of benefit from the
fact that you gave him the money. So according to רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda saying, no, no, no, that’s not going to be fine.
If it winds up that you kept the object, that you did
buy the field, then fine, keep the פירות. If it winds up
that he paid back the loan, pay back for the פירות that
he did. So why do the חכמים Chachamim not like it? חכמים
Chachamim not like it because in the interim it still looks like
ריבית. ribbis. I don't care that at the end of the day
you’re going to pay back the money, in the interim it looks
like ריבית, ribbis! so therefore the חכמים Chachamim don't even like it.
Okay, so that’s that debate about רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda about whether
we say צד אחד tzad echad according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
he goes so far to say that צד אחד בריבית tzad echad
b'ribbis as long as there’s one way out of it that’s okay
to make the whole thing not ריבית. ribbis Okay, now אמר רבא,
amar Rava, השתא דאמר רבי ינאי, hashta d'amar Rabbi Yannai, מה לי
הן מה לי דמיהן, whether I care about them, what do I
care about their money. So אמרינן נמי, aminan nami, so אמרינן, aminan,
so מה לי דמיהן מה לי
הן, mah li dmeihen mah li hen, אמרינן aminan מה לי דמיהן
מה לי הן, mah li dmeihen mah li hen, נמי אמרינן, nami
aminan, we also say, ופוסקין על שער שבשוק ואף על פי שאין
לו. u'poskin al sha'ar she-bashuk ve-af al pi she-ein lo. So he
says you can go back here and basically as long as you
can give money and basically even though the guy does not have
the fruit to give. Why? What makes that a sale? So he’s
conceptualizing it in the מה לי הן מה לי דמיהן. What makes
this a sale, even though the guy doesn't have fruit to give,
is because he can just as easily take the money that's in
his hands and that's like he's got the fruit already in his
hands. מה לי הן מה לי דמיהן, I could go ahead and
take this money and it could be fruit, meaning if you start
down here you sort of say, well, conceptually what allows you to,
to buy something even, you know even though delivery will be later
is that the guy is in possession of it. It could be
delivered even though money hadn't changed hands. Then they say, well, then
why does it work for money to change hands if the guy
isn't in possession? What made it a legitimate sale? Okay, now you
could have said okay it's as long as one of the things,
but what רבא is saying is, no, what makes this work conceptually
is מה לי דמיהן מה לי הן. mah li dmeihen mah li
hen. It's like he's in possession of it, he's got the cash
in his hands. He's got the cash in his hands, the stuff
is readily available in the marketplace, so therefore conceptually in this case
he's in possession and in this case he's also in possession. Okay,
so he didn't really tell you a new הלכה, Halacha, right, this
is as תוספות, Tos, as רשי Rashi points out, this is a
מפורש משנה meforash Mishnah later on, that if money changes hands you
can pre-sell the stuff to be delivered later. He's just saying conceptually,
it's based on this idea of מאי דמי הן מאי דמי הן,
mai dmei hen mai dmei hen, it's like he's already in possession
of it here because you gave him the money and now he
could use that money and that's like he's in possession of the
fruit.
The merchandise is readily available in the
marketplace and
he just has enough cash
to buy it. Exactly, exactly.
Exactly, exactly. So that's just to finish this point. Okay, ופסקינן כהשער
שבשוק, u'paskinan k'shaa shebashuk,
which is a משנה. Mishnah. ואף על פי שאין לו, ve'af al
pi she'ein lo, even though he doesn't have the product. אתו רב
פפא ורב הונא בריה דרב יהושע לרבא, Eisu Rav Pappa v'Rav Huna
b'reih d'Rav Yehoshua l'Rava, they asked him, כולם אם יש לו מותר
אם אין לו אסור. kulam im yesh lo mutar, im ein lo
assur.
Now we're just going to rehash what we said before.
One minute, we said that you could do the stuff only if
אם יש לו. im yesh lo. You can't do it if he
doesn't have—he actually literally has to have possession. אמר להו, Amar lehu,
התם הלוואה הכא זביני. Hasam hava, hacha v'inei.
Yes, here you have to be in possession because it started with
a loan. You said, 'Don't pay me back the money you owe
me.' So the thing that makes it a sale there, you need
possession of the product itself to make it a sale because no
money changed hands, it was just giving back a loan, so that
would be much more like a loan if somebody didn't have possession
of the product. But here where money changed hands, the other side
doesn't need possession because it's enough of a sale because you're actually
giving over money. We're just repeating what we said before. Because money
changed hands that makes it more of a sale, so that makes
it allowed even though you don't have possession. Because money doesn't change
hands and you're giving back a loan, it makes it much more
like a loan and it's only considered a sale if you have
possession of the product. Okay,
okay, it may sound like one of those movies about cocaine or
whatever: 'Do you have product? Are you in possession of the product?'
Okay, so אמר רבא, okay, okay, I know, it's so
exactly, okay. I was just saying
product, okay.
רבא ורב יוסף רמו אהדדי, Rava v'Rav Yosef ramu a'haddi, מאי טעמא
אמרו רבנן פוסקין על השער שבשוק ואף על פי שאין לו? mai
ta'ama amru rabbanan poskin al hashar shebashuk ve'af al pi she'ein lo?
Why did they say that you can make that arrangement even though
you don't have yet possession? דאמר ליה, de'amar lei, שקילא טיבותיך ושדיא
אחזיריי. shekila tivusayich v'shadya achzirei. Okay, because let's—here's what happens. I gave
David there a hundred dollars. Now he's going to come—and it was
ten dollars a bushel. He's going to come back and he's going
to give me ten bushels, and they're worth twelve dollars. So we
should say, 'Well, that looks like ריבית!' ribbis. I gave him a
hundred dollars, he gave me something worth a hundred twenty. No, it's
not really ריבית ribbis. because you know what I could say to
David? 'Take all of your, you know, the your, you know, whatever
good you're doing for me, take it and give it and throw
it to the pigs!' Okay, which is like, what is it? 'Pearls
before swine.' You love the range
of my references. Okay, so which is, take your goodness and throw
it, meaning what good did you do me? Oh, look, David gave
me a hundred twenty, something worth a hundred twenty, and I only
gave him a hundred. No, I didn't need David for that. My
honestly, what good did you do me? אי הוו זוזי בידי, ei
havi zuzei beyadi, had I not given you this hundred dollars two
months ago and I had kept that hundred
dollars, הוי מזבנינא בהיני ובשילי בזולא. havi mizbinina behini v'shili b'zula. I
could have gone to היני ושילי, Hini and Shili, which are apparently
these two towns in בבל Bavel which apparently sold wheat very cheap.
I could have gone and I could have bought the stuff at
a low price. So, oh, you know, what do you mean I
gave him a hundred and he gave me something back worth a
hundred and twenty? Had I never engaged in that transaction with him,
I just could have taken possession of the product at a lower
price and I could have made the profit myself. Now, of course,
what I would have had to do is I would have had
to hold on to all of that product, right?
Okay, what—they go on twenty now and get it in the same
place?
No, now I can't. Now the price has gone up. But what
I could have done is two months ago I could have bought
the product. Meaning so because—so I could have taken, what I'm saying
is it's not like I gave a hundred and got back a
hundred and twenty. I could have taken possession of the product two
months ago and I would have made the same money. Okay, so
therefore since you didn't really do me any favor, it's not like
I am making ריבית. ribbis. Of course, the difference is that then
I would have actually had to store the product, it would have
been effort. One minute, אמר ליה אביי לרב יוסף, amar lei Abaye
l'Rav Yosef, let's just finish this. אביי Abaye said to רב יוסף,
Rav Yosef, אלא מעתה מותר להלוות סאה בסאה, ela mei'ata, mutar l'havos
sa b'sa, משום דמצי אמר ליה שקילא טיבותיך ושדיא אחזיריי? shum d'mztzi
amei lei shekila tivusayich v'shadya achzirei? One minute, so how about I'm
not allowed to say to David—and this is the whole problem, can
I go to my next-door neighbor and say lend me two eggs?
Okay, I can't say to David,
'Lend me a whatever a pint
of—what's it—a pint of a pound of flour.' I can't say to
him lend me or let me a cup of flour and then
pay him back a cup of flour. Why? Because if he lends
me a cup of flour now and I go ahead and I
pay him back and then flour is worth more, he made some
money off of it. So why—we should allow that. Why should we
allow that? Because David could say to me, 'What did I gain
out of that transaction? I could have just held on to my
cup of flour, right?' Meaning if what we're saying is that anytime
the lender can say 'You didn't do me any favors here, it's
not...' not a problem, right? That's the argument, then it's not real
ריבית. ribbis. You didn't do me any favors! I could have held
on, I could have bought the wheat and taken possession there, so
you didn't do me any favors! I could have held onto the
flour, not lent you the flour, and I would have still had
the flour. So why is it a problem to lend you flour
and to get back the same cup of flour? That actually makes
a good argument, right?
תא שמע: Ta shema: מותר ללוות סאה בסאה mutar lilvos se'ah be'se'ah
משום דאמר ליה mishum de'amar lei שקול טיבותא ושדי אחצרי—take shekul tuvsa
u'shadi achatzrei your goods, take your favor and throw it and throw
it to the pigs. דאמר ליה: de'amar lei: חיטי דכדכדי באחלוואי? chiti
d'kadkadi ba'achalvayei?
What, would my wheat have rotted if it were in my storehouse?
Why because I lent it to you and I'm getting it back,
should that be a problem? You didn't do me any favors! I
could have just kept it in my storehouse. אמר ליה: Amar lei:
לא, התם הלוואה, הכא זביני. lo, hasam halva'ah, hacha zvini. No, no,
no,
here's the difference. There, it started as a loan. I said, "Lend
me a cup of flour." So lend, when we frame it as
a loan, it's more problematic and even if the lender doesn't benefit
from it, if in the end he gets back something that's worth
more, it's still a problem because it was framed as a loan
and that means that our antenna goes up much more quickly. Right?
Oh my god, he took a loan and he's getting back something
worth more, even if it didn't benefit the lender at all. But
here, where basically it starts as a purchase, I bought $100 worth
of wheat, you delivered $120 because you delivered it two months later,
there we could say fundamentally it's a purchase, it's not a loan.
And if I'm not really the lender, the guy giving out the
money—I'm the buyer, it's not the lender, the buyer—isn't really gaining anything,
he could have taken possession of the object, and so he's not
gaining anything from this whole transaction from getting it back two months
later, so then if it's both a מכר mecher fundamentally and he's
not gaining anything, we do not look at it as ריבית. ribbis,
Yes.
So that challenges the רש"י Rashi then, that it doesn't matter how
it starts, right?
Whether he's buying it or whether...
well, that's a good point. You mean because then if it starts
as a loan then... well, not רש"י, Rashi, the פסק psak then,
then you are gaining something because you couldn't have gone somewhere else
and taken possession of it.
Right, but maybe you could have said I could have taken possession
of it from you, rather than let you keep it for two
months and give it back to me two months later.
Right? I could have taken... you at least have the product to
give me. So it's not like I could have taken possession from
someone else, but it's a good point.
Another question was is it... do you have the... are you taking
the money that's being lent... am I taking the money that's being
lent and going and buying wheat or do I have wheat and
you're buying it from me? That's not...
let me just read two more lines just to get to the
two
dots. Okay. אמר ליה אדא בר אהבה לרבא: Amar lei Adda bar
Ahava le'Rava: והבא למיתב זוזי לספסירא—one v'haba le'misav zuzei l'safsira minute, if
I had not made this arrangement here with David, I'm saying like,
oh, I could have just bought it from somebody else and so
the fact that David's waiting two months to give me the wheat
isn't doing me any favors, I could have bought it from someone
else. So it says, no, if you were to go to somebody
else—and maybe you're right, Jenna, maybe this is partly also your issue,
but anyway—if you were going to somebody else, you'd have to give
money to somebody to act as the
middleman to find for you sellers. And therefore, therefore the fact that
you are
benefiting from not having to go through that whole process of actually
buying the product and taking possession of it and so on, so
you would have had to go ahead and do that, so you
are benefiting from this whole transaction. אמר ליה: Amar lei: דקיהיב ליה.
de'ka'yahiv lei. So the first answer is that actually I pay David
the money that I would have paid in the expenses of having
to go find other buyers. When I buy the stuff from him
for later delivery, I'm giving him also the money I'm saving
for other sellers, the money I'm saving by not having to go
ahead and put out ads in the paper to find other people
who are sellers, right? רב אשי Rav Ashi אמר... no, רב אשי'ס
Rav Ashi's answer: זוזי דאינשי אינהו עבדי ליה ספסירותא. zuzei d'inshi inhu
avdi lei safsirusa. People's money serves enough as their
middlemen. The fact that I have money to spend and I'm interested
in buying product, the sellers will come to me. I don't have
to expend any effort. People know that I have the money, they're
looking to sell their product. So therefore basically the argument again though
is, why are these types of transactions allowed? If there's enough of
an element that makes it look like a sale, or that reinforces,
I should say, that it is a sale—because that's what it is—either
money changed hands or one side has the product, then even though
in the end you're giving back something more than the money that
you took, but because it was a sale, and the argument being
that the person who gave out the money actually could have taken
possession of the product, isn't really gaining from the fact that you
waited the time, etc., could have just as easily have taken possession
of the product and sold it at a profit himself. So therefore
we do not view it as a type of ריבית. ribbis Yes.
Okay, it started as a sale and there really was fundamentally the
guy himself could have made the money on his own by using
the money himself to do that. Right? That's part of the reason
why you pay ריבית, ribbis. by the way. It's like, I'm giving
you the money to make money off of, I could have held
onto the money and made money myself. So they're almost saying it's
a sale, and the guy could have used the money to make
the same money on his own by taking possession of the product.
So therefore we're not going to look at it as ריבית ribbis.
and therefore it's going to be okay. All right. Now we're
going to get to another piece in the תוספתא. Tosefta. The תוספתא
Tosefta tells us another potential way. It says as follows, it's actually
in בבא מציעא Bava Metzia פרק ה. perek hei. There it says
המלוה את חברו, hamalveh es chaveiro, no, המלוה את חברו, hamalveh es
chaveiro, sorry, the language is different, המלוה את חברו hamalveh es chaveiro
on the condition שיהיה לו חלק ברווח sheyihiyeh lo chelek barevach that
he should have a share in the profit. And it says right
away and he doesn't have a share in the losses, meaning if
there's money to be made he gets a piece of the profit,
but if there are losses he is not taking any loss. So
the money is guaranteed. It says that's ריבית. That is forbidden. However,
if he takes both profit and loss then it's permitted. So now
we're getting into something very important. What happens if I'm not just
giving you the money to hold onto it, but I'm actually giving
you the money as an investment? I'm saying I'm going to give
you money to do some business and we will share the profit.
If we share the profit then the money is not a loan,
it's an investment. In that case, it's perfectly fine to take the
money because we are partners. Okay, let's look at it more closely.
When I give you money as an investment, what does that mean?
It means technically part of the money is a loan to you,
and part of the money is actually my money that you are
using to do business. That's really how we look at it. If
you're doing business with my money, then if there's profit, I'm entitled
to that profit because it's my money. But it also means that
if there's a loss, it's my loss as well because it's my
money. That is the core of what we call an עסקא, iska,
which is the root of the היתר עסקא. heter iska. An עסקא
iska is a partnership where one person provides the capital and the
other person provides the labor, the work. And then they share in
the profits and they share in the losses. As long as the
provider of the capital is sharing in the risk, then it's not
a loan. It is an investment, it's a partnership, and therefore any
profit that comes back to him is not ריבית. It's simply the
profit that his money earned. That is a very fundamental concept in
הלכות ריבית. hilchos ribbis.